<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-26T17:09:23+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fiebach Lab</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><author><name>Fiebach Lab</name></author><entry><title type="html">New paper published: Predicting intelligence from cortical gray matter volume</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New paper published: Predicting intelligence from cortical gray matter volume" /><published>2020-04-18T21:34:30+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-18T21:34:30+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-jekyll/"><![CDATA[<p>Statistically significant prediction (N = 308) but large prediction error questioning the practical value of VBM correlates of general intelligence.</p>

<p>A positive association between brain size and intelligence is firmly established, but whether region-specific anatomical differences contribute to general intelligence remains an open question. Results from voxel-based morphometry (VBM) - one of the most widely used morphometric methods - have remained inconclusive so far. Here, we applied cross-validated machine learning-based predictive modeling to test whether out-of-sample prediction of individual intelligence scores is possible on the basis of voxel-wise gray matter volume. Features were derived from structural magnetic resonance imaging data (N = 308) using (a) a purely data-driven method (principal component analysis) and (b) a domain knowledge-based approach (atlas parcellation). When using relative gray matter (corrected for total brain size), only the atlas-based approach provided significant prediction, while absolute gray matter (uncorrected) allowed for above-chance prediction with both approaches. Importantly, in all significant predictions, the absolute error was relatively high, i.e., greater than ten IQ points, and in the atlas-based models, the predicted IQ scores varied closely around the sample mean. This renders the practical value even of statistically significant prediction results questionable. Analyses based on the gray matter of functional brain networks yielded significant predictions for the fronto-parietal network and the cerebellum. However, the mean absolute errors were not reduced in contrast to the global models, suggesting that general intelligence may be related more to global than region-specific differences in gray matter volume. More generally, our study highlights the importance of predictive statistical analysis approaches for clarifying the neurobiological bases of intelligence and provides important suggestions for future research using predictive modeling.</p>

<p>Read more here: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00429-020-02113-7</p>]]></content><author><name>Fiebach Lab</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Statistically significant prediction (N = 308) but large prediction error questioning the practical value of VBM correlates of general intelligence.]]></summary></entry></feed>